<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><atom:link href="https://sankara.me/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><title>Sankara.Me</title><link>https://sankara.me/</link><description>An exercise in futility</description><lastBuildDate>Tue, 17 Jan 2023 03:35:44 +0000</lastBuildDate><generator>clj-rss</generator><item><guid>https://sankara.me/tech/adult-adhd/</guid><link>https://sankara.me/tech/adult-adhd/</link><title>ADHD as an adult</title><description>For as long as I could remember I have assumed that I procrastinate a lot.
On the other hand, if it's something fascinating, I'd find it
extremely hard to stop doing it. There was no in-between. I have also known
that I get distracted by the slightest stimulus and go in a complete tangent.
I'd do well in subjects I like and do pretty poorly in subjects I hate. I've
known that I'd space out a lot. Even when I really want to do something I'd
struggle to do it unless there's an immediate deadline or a payoff.
Surprisingly, I have also been told I'm a good listener - may be because in
reality my head's somewhere else. I could learn by listening to my brother
read (he had the habit of always reading out aloud) but taking the book and
reading it myself was always challenging. And yet somehow, I have done decently
well in school. Although, I still remember the look on my Principal's face when
I told him I got into a decent college. Every one of my teachers thought I had
the "potential" to shine if only I put in my effort.On the personal and relationships front, I would also say whatever comes to
mind without a filter. Since I could never hold a thought for more than a few
seconds, I'd blurt it out in fear that I'll forget it - only for it to come
across as cutting off someone and being rude. I could also never get social cues
as well as others. I almost faced disciplinary action at work as a result of
something I blurted out. I have missed out on so many dating opportunities
because I didn't understand the social signals well. While I can read people's
reaction to what I do and how it affects but could never predict this over an
impersonal medium like text/email - resulting in a lifelong list of lost
friendships and relationships. The only friendships that lasted are the ones
that really tolerated me and overlooked my infractions. I'd instantly react
emotionally to any criticism or feedback. I could almost never think on my
feet - I distinctly remember this as a kid.Unfortunately, those with whom you’re interacting don’t necessarily
know you have ADHD—or understand its role in causing your behavior—
and may see you as immature, self-centered, or egotistical.Barkley PhD, Russell A. Taking Charge of Adult ADHDThe first time I heard the word ADHD was when I was ~30. And even then I
didn't exactly connect with what I understood as ADHD -
hyperactivity/distracted. Neither did I understand how complex ADHD is and
how it extends to emotional intelligence. While I was trying to read books
on Emotional Intelligence and being a better person, I could never apply it
in real-life. All this changed a couple of years ago when I found this
video on reddit (of all the
places) by Dr. Russell Barkely.
I almost broke down crying realising how much of my life I have wasted
because - academically, professionally &amp; personally. Weirdly, it felt good
to know that there was indeed something wrong with me. Trying to fight this
all my life had been like a disabled person who doesn't know they're
disabled trying to climb a flight of stairs without even a crutch and not
understanding how others seem to have no issues walking up and down the stairs.The essence of it is that one or more
executive functions are underdeveloped in people with ADHD
.</description><author>Sankara</author><pubDate>Sun, 13 Nov 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><guid>https://sankara.me/tech/the-future-of-ai/</guid><link>https://sankara.me/tech/the-future-of-ai/</link><title>The Future of AI and Space Sci-Fi</title><description>There's an entire range of depictions when it comes to AI in space-travel themed science-fiction movies and TV shows. Hal, for example, is a conscious AI - for some definition of consciousness. While this is a wonderful plot device and something tech visionaries have been saying is right around the corner, it's not how I view AI at all.I think the show Expanse got it just right. All the ships and stations are loaded with AIs but you'd never even notice them. It's subtle. The AI does the job and gets out of the way. Take the example of intercepting missiles with PDCs or firing a rail gun. It's not a simple or trivial process (and the show goes to great lengths to make that clear as well). There are a huge variety of parameters to consider to keep the ship stable when it's firing its rail gun. This is space after all and Newton's third law can be a pita. Counteracting forces - via thrusters - are required in extreme precision to keep the ship from spinning or moving in any of the 3D space.Similarly, the countless other things to monitor in a ship and adjust automatically is the only way space travel would be possible with a reasonable crew. A very minor angle shift could mean the difference between reaching two entirely different planets and nothing's ever stationery in space.I also found it cool the way the crew interacts with the ship is depicted - a mix of voice commands and gestures and an AI that can interpret what they mean.  At least the way it’s depicted, they can also feed it "high level programming" - like Naomi creating a firing solution.My point is that none of this requires an AGI - Artificial General Intelligence - "just" an AI would do. It’s in by no means a ding. If we could replicate what evolution has taught animals to do, that in itself would be nothing short of a miracle.  If you think about it, a hummingbird with the brain the size of a pea, can flap its wings 53 times a second, maintain near perfect stillness, see things, hear things, dodge obstacles, seek out food and recognise what is good and what is not, identify danger, identify a mate and on and on. And the whole thing operates on a few grams of sugar.</description><author>Sankara</author><pubDate>Sat, 26 Jun 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><guid>https://sankara.me/gardening/setting-up-irrigation/</guid><link>https://sankara.me/gardening/setting-up-irrigation/</link><title>Gardening: Setting up Irrigation</title><description>The seeds are sprouting and growing much more rapidly than I thought it would.
With summer here the temperatures are hot, and the need for watering has gone
up. I figured it would be a good idea to setup irrigation to reduce water usage,
even watering and save some time.Even water pressure is much harder to achieve.
The irrigation systems on Amazon
come with 1/4" tubes. The pressure on these fizzle out with just a few atomizers
and sprinklers. The better option would be to run a 1/2" tube as the main line
and use the 1/4" tubes as feeder lines. Even that doesn't work beyond a point
especially when your house uses the same line to feed all faucets and taps.Next up is dealing with the stupid cat that wants to poop in my raised bed. A
net would provide the necessary barrier. I needed a frame to support the
net. This nifty hoops from Amazon
provided a decent frame, and it was extensible. It also doubled as the
supporting frame for the irrigation lines.Here's what it looks like:</description><author>Sankara</author><pubDate>Sun, 13 Jun 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><guid>https://sankara.me/gardening/starting-gardening/</guid><link>https://sankara.me/gardening/starting-gardening/</link><title>Starting a garden</title><description>The past weekend,
with a little help from my friends
, I started a vegetable garden in my backyard. It's been a really long time
since I did anything similar. The choice of what to plant was almost a lottery
pick. Maybe next time I'll learn to identify what makes sense to grow and what
to buy instead. Here are the first sprouts of some of them.CarrotCauliflowerHeirloom Cherry TomatoKohlrabiLavenderMarigoldMintOkraPomegranatePumpkinRadishRomaine LettuceTomatoSunflowerUnknown - Really - Forgot to label - Either basil or tomato or carrotWill share the progress and learnings.</description><author>Sankara</author><pubDate>Fri, 11 Jun 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><guid>https://sankara.me/wordsmith/chasing-success/</guid><link>https://sankara.me/wordsmith/chasing-success/</link><title>Chasing Success</title><description>Human brain has evolved to being lazy [1]. It's the natural state of
things. It is also more likely than not you're average - it's the very
definition of it. In our society, neither of this is adequate.Personally, there's a huge correlation between the rise of social media and the
feeling of inadequacy. Are you adequate in life? Are you married? Do you have a
wife? Do you own a home? Do you have kids? Are you a good parent to your kids?
Do you have friends? Are you a good friend? How many life skills do you know?
How many do you excel at? Can you cook? Do you read? How many books do you read
a year/week? Do you travel? How many countries have you travelled to? Are you a
manager yet? Do you love programming? Do you contribute to open-source? Are you
keeping yourself up to date with technology?We have become this society where it's not enough that we do something because
we like it/love it. We want to be the best at it or, more accurately, be better
than the people in your social circle. This has become even more acute with the
free time we have due to the pandemic. We're don't appreciate ourselves enought
for what we've learnt or achieved in general and especially so during this
trying times.We tend to correlate success with happiness. Ironically, we might find success
if we are happy, and we might be happier if we accept that an average existence
is a mighty good existence.</description><author>Sankara</author><pubDate>Wed, 03 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><guid>https://sankara.me/wordsmith/digital-minimalism/</guid><link>https://sankara.me/wordsmith/digital-minimalism/</link><title>Summary of Digital Minimalism</title><description>Digital Minimalism: Choosing a Focused Life in a Noisy WorldHello, I'm Sankara and I'm a social media and smartphone addict :). Social
media and smartphone are not always recognized as an addiction, at least not
clinically but the result is the same. They consume so much of our time and
influence our mood that at times we could fall behind on the things that
really matter. Even when I read the book I wasn't fully bought into the
philosophy of it. I mean I struggle with a lot of what the author had to say. I
even agree with and have personally seen the way my personal and professional
life is impacted by unchecked social media usage and even quit various social
media platforms as a result. However, I never fully took charge of my digital
life. The whole COVID situation only made it worse. This weekend (August 2020)
is when I finally decided to full on and minimize my phone usage to a minimum.
I'm not quitting everything in rage. I'd still stay connected. However, I'd
be making a clear plan on what I want to use, why and how much and stick to it.Why is too much digital exposure bad?</description><author>Sankara</author><pubDate>Sun, 23 Aug 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><guid>https://sankara.me/wordsmith/children-of-time/</guid><link>https://sankara.me/wordsmith/children-of-time/</link><title>Summary of Children of time</title><description>Children of time by Adrian Tchaikovskyhttps://www.goodreads.com/book/show/25499718-children-of-timeChildren of time is a fantastic creative novel by Adrian Tchaikovsky. Since this a summary of a thriller with a suspense
ending, you have to stop reading right now if you don't want to be ruined by a spoiler.Spoilers!!!
Spoilers!!!
Spoilers!!!The novel opens with a terraforming project (Brin) in a far away world lead by Dr. Avrana Kern. The goal of the
project is a scientific one - to investigate the possibility of giving intelligence to monkeys by introducing a virus
that accelerates certain desirable characteristics, primarily around cognition. However, this is not well received by
everyone. There's a lot of opposition to it in Earth. Unbeknownst to the crew of the project circling a world many light
years away from Earth, Earth has descended into wars between factions that support terraforming and experimentation and
those that are opposed to it. Also unknown to them is a mole within their ranks that's intent on destroying the entire
vessel and the crew with it.</description><author>Sankara</author><pubDate>Wed, 15 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><guid>https://sankara.me/wordsmith/radical-acceptance/</guid><link>https://sankara.me/wordsmith/radical-acceptance/</link><title>Summary of Radical Acceptance</title><description>Embracing Your Life With The Heart Of A Buddha by Tara Brach1. The Trance of UnworthinessWe live our world in a trance; inherent in this trance is the belief that no matter how hard we try we are always
falling short. This belief of unworthiness goes hand in hand with the alienation we feel from others and life. The
belief that we are unworthy makes it difficult to trust that we are truly loved. We also assume that our physical
sickness or emotional depression is our own fault.As you go through your day, pause occasionally to ask yourself, “This moment, do I accept myself just as I am?” Without
judging yourself, simply become aware of how you are relating to your body, emotions, thoughts and behaviors. As the
trance of unworthiness becomes conscious, it begins to lose its power over our lives.</description><author>Sankara</author><pubDate>Fri, 10 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><guid>https://sankara.me/wordsmith/why-do-this/</guid><link>https://sankara.me/wordsmith/why-do-this/</link><title>Why do this?</title><description>What's the motivation behind this blog?Like all ideas that are worthwhile, it came to me out of nowhere that I don't seem
to remember most of the things I read from a book. What's the point of
reading a book if we don't seem to be able to recall anything from it
by the time we reach the end of it? I realized I need a mechanism to
recollect and be able to reference. I already keep highlights and notes on Kindle.
So, why not try to distill them into an essay (or a collection of notes).
This is just an attempt at it.(Of course I also wanted to do this in Clojure and started building
my own blog engine to generate html from markdown and hosting it - Cryogen
had already solved it for me.)</description><author>Sankara</author><pubDate>Wed, 09 Oct 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate></item></channel></rss>